<!-- 

    Copyright (C)  2010  Sebastián Gurin.
    Permission is granted to copy, distribute and/or modify this document
    under the terms of the GNU Free Documentation License, Version 1.3
    or any later version published by the Free Software Foundation;
    with no Invariant Sections, no Front-Cover Texts, and no Back-Cover Texts.
    A copy of the license is included in the section entitled "GNU
    Free Documentation License".

@author: sgurin 

-->


<chapter id="working-with-native-code">


  <title>Working With native code</title>
  
<!--  <epigraph>-->
<!--<attribution>William James</attribution>-->
<!--<para>-->
<!--Action may not bring happiness but there is no happiness without action.-->
<!--</para>-->
<!--</epigraph>-->
  
  
  <para>in section we have explained how to use J2S compiler directives like @j2sNative inside javadocs
  for customizing compiler output code, and specially the directive @j2sNative for including 
  native javascript in our java classes.</para>
  
  <para>Nevertheless, there are some areas that need to be understand if you want to write 
  native javascript code and need to integrate that native code with your java code.
  
  
  </para>  
  
<!--   stasks that are not so tribial to do. Take for example a very  common problem: register a mouse click listener -->
  <para>this chapter will describe how, call java methods from javascript code, problems with java object+method vs - javascript objectsand javascript functions, care native objects like dom, etc, </para>
  <para>TODO</para>
  
  <para>j2s-native-mode support is expl here</para>
  
  <section><title>Native Objects</title>
  <para>a native object is TODO</para>
  <para>why we have to be careful when dealing with native objects?</para>
  <para>TODO</para>  
<!--    <tip><para>When working with native objects, try to encapsulate them in a private variable</para></tip>-->
  
  </section>
  
   <section>
    <title>Accessing native JavaScript objects from Java</title>

    <para>In section <link endterm="section-writing-native-js-code-with-j2snative-title"
    linkend="section-writing-native-js-code-with-j2snative"></link> we learn how to include our
    JavaScript code in our Java classes and how our native JavaScript code can
    call our Java objects. But, wait a moment, in JavaScript we have access to
    a the document object model, and a lot of JavaScript utilities and
    toolkits .... TODO  </para>

    <para>In Java, all objects are inherited from Java.lang.Object. So they must
    implement methods like hashCode(), equals(), etc. We say that an object is
    native when it is created from native JavaScript code and doesn't
    implements java.lang.Object.   .... TODO</para>
    
  </section>
  
  
   
   
    <section><title>Native objects mode support</title>
    
    <para>By default, J2S will overwrite javascript Object.prototype adding methods of java.lang.Object like equals, hashCode, notifyAll, etc, 
    so all created objects are valid java objects. Normally this is fine because you don't have to worry
    about javascript objects that are not valid java objects. </para>
    
    <para>Nevertheless, in some situations, this default behaviour is not desiderable. For example, 
    if you want to integrate your J2S application with a 3rd party javascript toolkit, there can be compatibilities issues because some 
    javascript toolkits simply don't work with a modified Object.prototype. More, since all javascript objects
    contains java.lang.Object methods, it is impossible to create a clean javascript object, something really 
    common and required for working with 3rd party javascript toolkits. </para>
    
    <para>Fortunately J2S supports a "native object" mode, in which javascript Object.prototype is not contaminated</para>
    <para>explain the problems with native objects and explain j2s.native mode</para>
    
    </section>
    
    
    
    
    
    
    
    
    
    
    
    
    
    
    
    
    
    
    
    
    <section><title>JavaScript functions</title>
    <para>TODO: this sections contains the escense but has a bad english. it should be rewritten more elegantly.</para>
<!-- summary: 
explain the problems of javascript functions. 
    1) emulated in java with runnable, but a runnable is not a function!! 
    2) problem with function context in java   -->


<!-- the language problem -->
    <para>The first problem that we face when working with native javascript is that , in javascript, we work with 
    functions and the java language doesn't support such a concept or nothing similar. In java, the only beahaviour language concepts we have are 
    instance methods and static methods. Mixing native javascript functions and java code without realizing what we really are doing,
    can cause very nasty bugs and problems, and so in this section we will examine possible problems and advices about how to do it right.
   </para>   
   
<!--   the function context problem-->

   <para>function context:</para>
   <para>what is a function context? In javascript, any function can be evaluated using any object as its context. The context of a 
   function when evaluated is the object referenced by the "this" keyword.</para>
   
   <important><para>Javascript function can be called with an arbitrary context object while Java instance 
   methods must always have a fixed context. </para></important>
   
    <para>since in java we always have to use an object, the function in java have a fixed context (the this object). 
    But in javascript this is not true and we must ensure the context. for example, the following example for registering a
    mouse click listener in document.body will work, but it is incorrect! :</para>
    
    <programlisting>
Runnable r = new Runnable(){
  public void run() {
    System.out.println("clicked");
  }
};
/**
 * @j2sNative
 * document.body.onclick=r.run; //WRONG!
 */{}
    </programlisting>
    
    <para>Why this is wrong? When an html document is clicked, and a function is registered for listen to clicks with "element.onclick", 
    the function will be evaluated using the clicked html element as the function context. This means that any reference to "this" in the function body, will
    point to the target html element and not where it should be, to the Runnable instance. Let examine an example that fails because of this:</para>
    
    <programlisting></programlisting>
    
    <para>With java static methods there is no problem because they do no context (no this pointer). But it is not useful to work with 
    static methods for </para>
    
    
    </section>
    
    
<!--  <section><title>j2s-base project for doing javascript in java</title></section>-->
   
</chapter>
