
<chapter id="chap-about-this-document">

<title>About this document</title>

<para>This document is currently a <emphasis>WORK in PROGRESS</emphasis>. paragraphs and section contains the work <emphasis>TODO</emphasis> mean that the section is to be written or lacks revision.</para>
  
  <para>Document format links (TODO)</para>
  
  <para>The following is a list with summaries about each chapter contents:</para>
  
  <itemizedlist>
  
    <listitem>
    <para><xref linkend="chap-intro"/> Introduces Java2Script product</para>
    </listitem>
    
    <listitem><para><xref linkend="chap-getting-started"/> Teach the user, step by step how 
    to create its first Java2Script application, how to execute it in the browser, 
    and the basics about Java2Script application projects.
    </para></listitem>
  
  
    <listitem><para><xref linkend="chap-java-to-js-translation"/>&nbsp; deepens on how java code is translated by Java2Script compiler into JavaScript. 
    Details how a Java2Script application is loaded in an html document with javascript.</para></listitem>
    
    <listitem><para>In <xref linkend="chap-j2s-plugin"/>&nbsp; we give detailed description of all functionalities of 
    Java2Script eclipse plugin, reviewing each component of the plugin and each plugin capability. </para></listitem>
    
    
    <listitem><para>In <xref linkend="chap-java-support"/>&nbsp; we will talk about java language and standard 
    library support in javas2cript. An detailed list of each supported class and method of java.lang, 
    java.util, java.io, etc is presented.  </para></listitem>
    
    <listitem><para><xref linkend="chap-integrated-libs"/> &nbsp;explains how to use java libraries 
    supported by Java2Script like SWT, jUnit, etc. </para></listitem>
    
    <listitem><para><xref linkend="using-j2s-compiler-directives"/> &nbsp;explains how to customize Java2Script 
    compiler output using JavaDoc @j2s special tags. </para></listitem>
    
    <listitem><para><xref linkend="working-with-native-code"/>&nbsp;gives details about using JavaDoc tag @j2sNative 
    for embedding native javascript code. Gives information and recommendations about using native objects in java code.  </para></listitem>
    
    <listitem><para><xref linkend="chap-client-server-comunicacion"/> Describe Java2Script facilities for
    client-server communication, like RPC, simple pipe, comment and doing normal ajax in Java2Script applications.-</para></listitem>


    <listitem><para><xref linkend="chap-j2s-sources"/>&nbsp;contains step by step guide on working with Java2Script
    plugin sources so the user may debug the plugin and customize it or simply know the plugin's internals.</para></listitem>
        
    <listitem><para><xref linkend="app-java-emulation-api"/>&nbsp;gives detailed information about Java2Script java language and java runtime 
    javascript emulation, documenting methods of Clazz for java language emulation and ClazzLoader for java runtime emulation.</para></listitem>
     
     <listitem><para><xref linkend="app-fdl"/>&nbsp;contains the full text of the license used for releasing this book.</para></listitem>
     
  </itemizedlist>
  
</chapter>